<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ben Kellman</title>
    <link>https://bkellman.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ben Kellman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Ben Kellman</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://bkellman.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/home/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/home/about/</guid>
      <description>About Today, Ben is a Ph.D. student in Bioinformatics and Systems Biology at the University of California, San Diego working in the Lewis Lab for Systems Biology and Cell Engineering. He is published and working in the application of systems biological perspectives in glycobiology.
His published work in Necrotizing Enterocolitis is the first study to reproduce preclinical protection of human milk sugars in humans. This work can hopefully be used to identify, prevent and treat this disease but also creates a new president to further examine human milk sugars, a clinically underappreciated biotherapeutic, as a new mode of clinical action.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent Publications</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/home/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/home/publications/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Recent &amp; Upcoming Talks</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/home/talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/home/talks/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Projects</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/home/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/home/projects/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>News</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/home/news/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/home/news/</guid>
      <description> 2017, AAAS members stand up for science - Michaela Jarvis, Science 2017, UCSD Student Bikes From San Diego to San Francisco to Raise Money for Science - Cassia Pollock, NBC 2017, Bike for Science - Kenza Sidi-Ali-Cherif, AAAS  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fun</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/home/fun/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/home/fun/</guid>
      <description>  Mountain Bike Racing  2017 Kenda Cup West Champion for cross-country mountain biking, category 3, men 25-29 2016 California State Champion for cross-country mountain biking, category 3, men 25-29   Coding  Double Tetris  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/home/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/home/contact/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human Milk Oligosaccharides, Infant Health and Maternal Blood Groups</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/talk/nec_hmo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/talk/nec_hmo/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Essentiality, Synthesis, and Prediction in Glycobiology</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/talk/advancement/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/talk/advancement/</guid>
      <description>Click here to see the full written proposal</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exhaustive Modeling of Human Milk Oligosaccharide (HMO) Biosynthesis – Nathan Lewis, Lars Bode</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/project/hmosyn/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/project/hmosyn/</guid>
      <description>[in prepreation]
Human Milk Oligosaccharides (HMOs) are abundant and functionally important components of human milk. A growing body of evidence suggests these glycans have major impacts on the health and development of the breastfed infant. Although they were discovered more than half a century ago, their biosynthesis in the human mammary gland remains minimally characterized. We propose to develop a framework for predicting which glycosyltransferases are involved in HMO biosynthesis and identify candidate structures for poorly characterized HMOs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Systematic Evaluation of Methods for Tailoring Genome-Scale Metabolic Models</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/publication/tissue-specific-metabilic-modeling/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/publication/tissue-specific-metabilic-modeling/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human milk oligosaccharide composition predicts risk of necrotising enterocolitis in preterm infants</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/publication/nec-hmo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/publication/nec-hmo/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AAAS: Give Science a Voice Ride</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/project/aaas-give-science-a-voice-ride/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/project/aaas-give-science-a-voice-ride/</guid>
      <description>A fundraiser for AAAS&amp;rsquo; office of government relations. AAAS is an foundational organization responsible for publishing the magazine Science. Importantly, they are in DC advocating for the funding and use of rigorously obtained information; they advocate for &amp;ldquo;evidence-based reasoning.&amp;rdquo;
Social Media Follow us on our facebook page
Follow us on twitter or instagram at #bike4science
Considering joining the next ride? Let us know today Why raise money for AAAS Today, advocates need money to be heard by our representatives.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human Milk Oligosaccharide (HMO) composition in relation to risk of Necrotizing Enterocolitis (NEC) – Nathan Lewis, Lars Bode</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/project/nec-hmo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/project/nec-hmo/</guid>
      <description>published 2017
A follow up on findings showing the mitigation of Necrotizing Enterocolitis (NEC) in a mouse model after administration of combined Human Milk Oligosaccharide (HMO) as well as a single HMO: DSLNT. We found that consecutive depletion of DSLNT in the mother’s milk was correlated with NEC onset in the infant. This finding is consistent with the pre-clinical rat model suggesting that DSLNT provides a significant protective effect for preterm infants from NEC.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pediatric Diagnostics: Managing Heterogeneity with Systems Biology</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/talk/pediatricsystemsmedicine/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/talk/pediatricsystemsmedicine/</guid>
      <description>Click here to see the full written proposal</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>