<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gene Expression on Ben Kellman</title>
    <link>https://bkellman.github.io/tags/gene-expression/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Gene Expression on Ben Kellman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Ben Kellman</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://bkellman.github.io/tags/gene-expression/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Exhaustive Modeling of Human Milk Oligosaccharide (HMO) Biosynthesis – Nathan Lewis, Lars Bode</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/project/hmosyn/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/project/hmosyn/</guid>
      <description>[in prepreation]
Human Milk Oligosaccharides (HMOs) are abundant and functionally important components of human milk. A growing body of evidence suggests these glycans have major impacts on the health and development of the breastfed infant. Although they were discovered more than half a century ago, their biosynthesis in the human mammary gland remains minimally characterized. We propose to develop a framework for predicting which glycosyltransferases are involved in HMO biosynthesis and identify candidate structures for poorly characterized HMOs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Human Milk Oligosaccharide (HMO) composition in relation to risk of Necrotizing Enterocolitis (NEC) – Nathan Lewis, Lars Bode</title>
      <link>https://bkellman.github.io/project/nec-hmo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://bkellman.github.io/project/nec-hmo/</guid>
      <description>published 2017
A follow up on findings showing the mitigation of Necrotizing Enterocolitis (NEC) in a mouse model after administration of combined Human Milk Oligosaccharide (HMO) as well as a single HMO: DSLNT. We found that consecutive depletion of DSLNT in the mother’s milk was correlated with NEC onset in the infant. This finding is consistent with the pre-clinical rat model suggesting that DSLNT provides a significant protective effect for preterm infants from NEC.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>